

João de Jesus Costa

Software Engineer



Santa Maria da Feira, Portugal



+351 912768196



joaocosta.dev



joaocosta.work@posteo.net



www.linkedin.com/in/joaocostaifg



github.com/JoaoCostaIFG

About me —

I'm a software engineer with a Master's degree in Informatics Engineering at FEUP. My interests mainly reside in developing software, taking care of my servers, writing (I have a blog), and developing projects using microcontrollers. I have experience working in large and fully-remote teams, and publicly presenting my work and ideas.

Skills ————

Hard skills ————

C - C++

Linux - DevOps

Python

Java

JavaScript - TypeScript

Language skills -

Portuguese

C1

Native

Soft skills -

English

problem-solving flexibility communication

Hobbies/Interests

On my free-time, I'm usually working on personal projects involving informatics and (sometimes) electronics. Often, these projects lead to contributions to open-source software. I also enjoy maintaining a personal home-server and a blog focused on tech.

Education

2021 - 2023 **Master in Informatics Engineering**

Final grade 18/20

2018 - 2021 **Bachelor of Science**

Final grade 18/20

Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto (FEUP)

Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto (FEUP)

Publications

2023 Verification of the VxWorks real-time operating system for DO-178C compliance

> My Master's thesis. The objective of this thesis was to analyze and optimize the processes of the real-time OS verification team at Critical Software. This resulted in a list of bottlenecks and action to address them, and the development of solutions/tools for some problems.

Awards

2018 Award for highest grade in highs cool

2018 Merit scholarship from Amorim Cork Composites

Work experience

2022-current **Embedded Software Engineer**

Embedded Software Engineer working on the verification and validation of embedded software for the aerospace industry. Started working at this position for my Master's thesis. The objective of this thesis was to analyze and optimize the processes of the project's developer team. This was achieved by identifying the bottlenecks and developing solutions/tools.

2022 Software Developer Intern Critical Software

Enrolled in the summer internship program at Critical Software (Summer Camp), with the objective of learning more about the company's activities, and developing softskills. Developed three projects, and attended multiple workshops during this onemonth internship.

2020-2021 Web Game Developer

Responsible from the team tasked to recreate a set of educational games, developed in flash, in the Unity game engine. These games were then hosted in the company's website to be played by children (aged 6 to 14) at school. Developed the games in C# for the Unity game engine, with an emphasis on performance so the games ran on WebGL on lower-end computers.



João de Jesus Costa

Software Engineer



Santa Maria da Feira, Portugal



+351 912768196



ioaocosta.dev



joaocosta.work@posteo.net



www.linkedin.com/in/joaocostaifg



github.com/JoaoCostaIFG

About me -

I'm a software engineer with a Master's degree in Informatics Engineering at FEUP. My interests mainly reside in developing software, taking care of my servers, writing (I have a blog), and developing projects using microcontrollers. I have experience working in large and fully-remote teams, and publicly presenting my work and ideas.

Skills —

Hard skills ————

C - C++

Linux - DevOps

Python

Java

JavaScript - TypeScript

Language skills -

Portuguese Native

English C1

Soft skills ————

problem-solving flexibility communication

Projects

2022 TraSMAPy

Project's GitHub page

A Python API for the SUMO traffic simulator with the objective of allowing researchers with limited knowledge in informatics and programming to model road traffic simulations. The API abstracts lower level concepts of the simulator and builds new concepts to make it easier to build agent-based simulations,

2022 uKerne

Project's GitHub page

A real-time micro-kernel for the Arduino UNO supporting POSIX style tasks, mutexes, EDF scheduling, task sleeping, and assertions. Responsible for most of the implementation and research for the project.

2021 Dry Beans classification

Project's GitHub page

Model (unsupervised learning) to classify beans between seven classes with similar features. This served as an opportunity to gain experience in data science and machine learning libraries for python. Responsible for part of the data analysis and treatment, the application of unsupervised learning algorithms, and the comparison of the results.

2021 Segmentation Fault

Project's GitHub page

Online QA web application resembling StackOverflow. This project was developed with the purpose of learning Bootstrap, Docker, Laravel, and PostgreSQL. Responsible for the Docker image, database design and indexes, most of the front-end, and accessibility/design choices.

2020-2021 MAWW

Project's GitHub page

Program that allows users (using X11) on Linux to have animated backgrounds, regardless of their compositor. This project is available as an Arch Linux package on the AUR.